Guide to the Victor Gifford Audubon Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Victor Gifford Audubon collection
1845-1859
GEN MSS 343
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Collection includes correspondence between Victor Gifford Audubon and Daniel Rice, a book subscription agent, regarding the production and sale of the works of John James Audubon. Also included are 22 uncolored, 8 partially tinted and 2 hand-colored lithographed plates for the octavo edition of "The Birds of North America," all by John T. Bowen after Audubon; 3 additional hand-colored plates, also by Bowen after Audubon, which may have served as colorist's proofs or models; and a group of 19 pencil and watercolor portraits and drawings by an unidentified artist.
Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1993 from the William Reese Company on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
See also the Morris Tyler Family Collection of John James Audubon, GEN MSS 85.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Victor Gifford Audubon, son of the illustrator and naturalist John James Audubon, was born on June 12, 1809. As an adult he assisted his father, along with his brother John Woodhouse Audubon, in the creation of The Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America. While he did contribute some artistic work to the project, his main function was to handle the business of producing and selling the work, along with the earlier The Birds of America. After his father's death, Victor continued to manage the business aspects in promoting his father's work. He died in 1862.
Scope and Contents
The Victor Gifford Audubon Collection contains correspondence, lithographed plates, and drawings. The collection has been arranged into two series.
Series I, Correspondence (1845-1859), consists of letters from Victor Gifford Audubon to Daniel Rice, a book subscription agent and co-publisher of History of the Indian Tribes of North America by Thomas L. M'Kenney and James Hall, which is referred to in several letters. The letters concern the business relationship between Rice and Audubon regarding the printing, binding, distribution and sale of the octavo-format editions of The Birds of America and The Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America by John James Audubon. Issues discussed include the ongoing business agreement between Audubon and Rice, sales trips taken by Rice, Audubon's efforts to convince Rice to buy a share of the volumes being produced, the supply of letterpress text, and difficulties in collecting payments from subscribers. Included is a signed agreement (Box 1, folder 1) between Audubon and Rice regarding Rice's seeking subscribers for the two books, and his commission for their sale. Also included are letters from Audubon to an H. J. Hall, A. M. Hart (Rice's partner), and one letter from Harper Brothers to Rice regarding a claim against a Mr. Mygatt, who is mentioned in several of Audubon's letters to Rice.
Series II, Illustrations (n.d.), contains lithographed plates used in the octavo version of The Birds of America, some hand-colored, and a group of pencil and pencil and watercolor sketches by an unidentified artist.
Drawings (visual works); Lithographs; Watercolors (paintings); The Birds of America; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860; Bowen, John T., approximately 1801-1856?; Rice, Daniel
- Correspondence, 1845-59; Series I; 0.2' (1/2 box)
  - LETTERS FROM VICTOR GIFFORD AUDUBON
    - Rice, Daniel, 1845-59 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - Hall, H. J., 1851 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hart, A. M., 1856 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Harper Brothers to Daniel Rice, 1853 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Illustrations, n.d.; Series II; 0.2' (1/2 box)
  - LITHOGRAPHS FOR THE BIRDS OF AMERICA
    Scope and Contents
    By John T. Bowen after John James Audubon
    - 22 uncolored lithographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - 8 partially colored (backgrounds only) lithographs (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 2 finished hand-colored lithographs (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Possibly proofs or samples furnished to Daniel Rice
    - 3 finished hand-colored lithographs (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Plates may have served as colorist's proofs or models since the margins show test strokes of various water- color pigments
  - OTHER ILLUSTRATIONS
    - 19 pencil sketches and pencil and watercolor sketches by an unidentified artist (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
      Subjects include portraits, sailing ships, and landscapes